## **Steve Herrin**

CONTACT Information jobs@steveherrin.com

650-814-8865 San Jose, CA www.github.com/steveherrin www.linkedin.com/in/herrinsteve

SUMMARY

Engineering leader with over a decade of experience using software, data, and machine learning to solve novel scientific and technological problems. Experience building and managing engineering and data teams. Scientific (physics PhD) background with demonstrated adaptibility to other fields like biotech.

EXPERIENCE

## D2G Oncology, Mountain View, CA

April 2021 - present

Staff Software Engineer

- Created in silico simulations of PCR and sequencing, used for oligo design, QC, and automated processing of several multiplexed sequencing runs per month
- Built a pipeline using pydantic to automate ETL and validation of Benchling LIMS data from an HTTP API to a PostgreSQL warehouse
- Developed a Python API library exposing GraphQL and REST hooks for accessing and traversing the relations of a large knowledge graph of lab, sequencing, and analysis data, as well as external data sets

## 23andMe, Sunnyvale, CA

January 2014 - March 2021

Engineering Individual Contributor (~5 years; final title: sr. tech lead engineer)

- Built HTTP API and web app that allowed internal and external researchers to dynamically query *k*-anonymized data stored in HBase for >5 million customers using a SQL-like interface
- Migrated a 20 kLOC Django web application to the AWS cloud, upgrading the back-end from Python 2 to 3 and standardizing the front-end using React and Typescript
- Designed and implemented a Python library providing a unified API for accessing customer data across MySQL, HBase, and other data stores, eventually used for 100% of customer content
- Created Genotyping Services, a Django webapp on AWS allowing external researchers to easily run genomic studies, increasing sales by over 2% and leading to strategic data-sharing agreements
- Architected and led building of containerized (Docker, AWS ECS) systems to ensure quality, reproducibility, and rapid deployment of machine learning models, used for over 90% of production models
- Built 3 generations of distributed data pipelines with Celery, Luigi, and AWS Simple Workflow to run Python, C++, and R algorithms that impute, transform, and analyze petabytes of genetic data
- Developed and automated a maximum likelihood analysis combining private and public datasets that flagged  $\sim 0.5\%$  of genotyping probes as bad for replacement in future platforms
- Automated genotype calling using a combination of unsupervised and supervised ML techniques

Engineering Management (~2 years; title: engineering manager)

- Created and recruited for 3 machine learning and data -focused engineering teams totaling 16 engineers, including a mix of leads, senior, and junior level individual contributors
- Formed and led team of engineering leads to standardize interviewing guidelines and open source release processes, subsequently adopted by all engineering teams

## Insight Data Science, Mountain View, CA

August 2013 – December 2013

Postdoctoral Fellow

• Developed Parksafely, a web app applying a heuristic algorithm to make bike rack recommendations on a map, reducing bike theft risk by 40% while requiring only 150 ft more walking on average. Used Flask, PostgreSQL/PostGIS, and Javascript.

Research Associate

- Applied machine learning algorithms & statistical analysis to improve detector energy resolution by 25%
- Repurposed the detector for 3D cosmic ray muon reconstruction using computer vision algorithms, yielding a 10x reduction in cosmogenic background uncertainty
- Created a PHP logbook webapp with a MySQL backend for tracking work on the EXO-200 experiment
- Built, networked, and programmed PLC control systems using over 600 channels of heterogeneous sensor data at a site with unreliable internet connectivity, successfully protecting \$10M of liquid xenon
- Developed batch data pipelines using Python, C++, and shell scripts to routinely measure detector characteristics by processing TB of calibration data.
- · Coordinated hardware and analysis software development with remote teams distributed around the world
- Mentored 1–2 junior graduate students (at any given time) on lab, coding, and statistical technique

Rice University, Houston, TX

May 2005 – May 2007

and University of Washington, Seattle, WA

June 2006 - August 2006

Undergraduate Research Assistant

• Implemented (in C++) and evaluated random forest and boosted decision tree algorithms that contributed to the discovery of single top quark production by Fermilab's D0 experiment

SKILLS

Languages: Python, Rust, C++, SQL, \*NIX Shell Scripting, Elm, JavaScript, TypeScript, R

**Tools:** AWS, NumPy, SciPy, Scikit-Learn, Pydantic, FastAPI, Flask, Django, React, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Git, HBase, Spark, LaTeX

**Other:** Machine Learning, Data Analysis, Statistics, Simulation, CI/CD, Sensors, Neutrino & Particle Physics, Analog & Digital Electronics, Radio (Amateur Extra License), Experienced Underground Miner

OPEN SOURCE

SpookyOTP: A lightweight Python implementation of TOTP/HOTP authentication

EDUCATION

Stanford University, Stanford, CA

June 2013

• Ph.D. (Physics)

Rice University, Houston, TX

May 2007

• B.S. (Physics)